<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Dolphins danger and deliuerance being a ship of 220. tunne hauing in her but 36. men and 2. boyes, who were on the 12. of Ianuary 1616. set vpon by 6. men of warre of the Turkes hauing at the least 1500. men in them : who fought with them 5. houres and a halfe, yet to the glory of God and the honor of our English nation, both shippe and goods safely brought vp the Riuer of Thames and deliuered / truely set forth by the appoyntment of M. Edward Nichols, being Maister of the said ship ; with the names of all those that were slaine on the English part, the maner how, and how many were maymed, and what they are that suruiue.</title>
            <author>Nichols, Edward, fl. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23748.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21465335</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21465335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24000</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24000)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1737:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Dolphins danger and deliuerance being a ship of 220. tunne hauing in her but 36. men and 2. boyes, who were on the 12. of Ianuary 1616. set vpon by 6. men of warre of the Turkes hauing at the least 1500. men in them : who fought with them 5. houres and a halfe, yet to the glory of God and the honor of our English nation, both shippe and goods safely brought vp the Riuer of Thames and deliuered / truely set forth by the appoyntment of M. Edward Nichols, being Maister of the said ship ; with the names of all those that were slaine on the English part, the maner how, and how many were maymed, and what they are that suruiue.</title>
                  <author>Nichols, Edward, fl. 1617.</author>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Gosson, and are to be solde in Panier Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Epistle signed: Edvvard Nicholls.</note>
                  <note>"A toothlesse satire vpon him that made, or rather mard the former booke" signed: Iohn Taylor, p. [5]-[6].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dolphin (Ship)</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Dolphins danger: and Deliuerance. Being a Ship of 220. Tunne hauing in her but 36. Men and 2. Boyes, who were on the 12. of Ianuary 1616. ſet vpon by 6. Men of Warre of the Turkes hauing at the leaſt 1500. Men in them, who fought with them 5. houres and a halfe, yet to the glory of God and the honor of our Engliſh Nation, both Shippe and goods ſafely brought vp the Riuer of Thames and deliuered. Truely ſet forth by the appoyntment of M. Edward Nichols, being Maiſter of the ſaid Ship. With the names of all thoſe that were ſlaine on the Engliſh part, the maner how, and how many were maymed, and what they are that ſuruiue.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Henry Goſſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde in Panier Alley. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a ship</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:2"/>
            <head>To the High and mighty <hi>Charles</hi> Prince of Wales, Duke of Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, Yorke, and Albanie, Earle of Cheſter, and Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Gracious Prince, (I your humble Vaſſall) beeing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened by your innated gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous acceptation of all good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, to preſent your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with this poore piece of a ſhadow of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall perills that I haue eſcaped, which for my part had neuer beene publiſhed, but that it was falſly printed without my knowledge; which for the regard I haue to the truth and mine owne Credit, I could doe no leſſe then contradict with a Refutation of falſhood. I humbly implore
<pb facs="tcp:24000:3"/>your Highnes to beſtow your gracious reading of the infallible verity of the truth, which if you vouchſafe, you ſhall therein ſee Gods power manifeſted when man is at the weakeſt. So wiſhing your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes all earthly and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly felicity, I remaine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble and obedient Seruant. EDWARD NICNOLLS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:3"/>
            <head>A Toothleſſe Satire vpon him that made, or rather mard the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Booke.</head>
            <l>RIch cloath of gold vnto a Botcher brought,</l>
            <l>It ſhall be mard, not made, quite ſham'd, not fram'd:</l>
            <l>When worſer ſtuffe by a good Worke-man wrought,</l>
            <l>Becomes the owner, makes the maker fam'd.</l>
            <l>Rare Phiſicke, as it is as abus'd, or vs'd,</l>
            <l>As is the Doctors ignorance, or skill:</l>
            <l>Such operation from it is infus'd,</l>
            <l>That it doth helpe, or hurt, or cure, or kill.</l>
            <l>Vnto the ſtuffe the fault we cannot put,</l>
            <l>Nor to the Phiſicke, we the crime apply:</l>
            <l>The Bungling Taylor ſpoyld when he did cut,</l>
            <l>And want of skill did cauſe the patient dye.</l>
            <l>Then let a botching patcher botch and mend,</l>
            <l>Let Mountebankes giue Phiſicke vnto dogs:</l>
            <l>Let Coopers on their hooples Tubs attend,</l>
            <l>And Millers deale no further then their Cogges.</l>
            <l>For, when a witles Rooke ſhall vndertake,</l>
            <l>Of ſuch exployts as theſe to make a Booke:</l>
            <l>The ancient Prouethe true, he ſeeme to make</l>
            <l>God ſends good meat, the Diuell ſends a Cooke.</l>
            <l>Why, ſuch a worke as this deſerues to haue</l>
            <l>A <hi>Homers,</hi> or a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgils</hi> skill to grace in</l>
            <l>And not an ignorant intruding K----</l>
            <l>Whoſe blindnes did in euery place miſplace it.</l>
            <l>Some lies ſome truthes together cram'd and thruſt,</l>
            <l>Quite out of Time, like muſtard after meat:</l>
            <l>That 'tis a wonder ſuch a fellow durſt</l>
            <l>VVith wit ſo little, write of things ſo great.</l>
            <l>VVhere thirty ſixe men and two boyes in fight,</l>
            <l>Gainſt fifteene hundred were ſixe houres oppos'd:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:4"/>
            <l>Boorded with multitudes; with maine and might,</l>
            <l>Round with the foes, and fiery flames inclos'd</l>
            <l>Where death was ſcorn'd and vallour was belou'd,</l>
            <l>Where victory was that, at which they aym'd;</l>
            <l>Where noble Reſolution was aproou'd</l>
            <l>Where Fame adornes, the ſound, dead, hurt and maim'd,</l>
            <l>What ſubiect could a pen more Ample find</l>
            <l>(If all were written in perticular)</l>
            <l>From Thames, vnto the fartheſt ſhore of Inde,</l>
            <l>Or from the Artick toth' Antartick ſtarre.</l>
            <l>Why ſhould a fellow, beeing there in place,</l>
            <l>Remember not himſelfe, or any other;</l>
            <l>But bury all their glory in diſgrace,</l>
            <l>And each mans Acts in darke obliuion ſmother:</l>
            <l>O! tis a hell of hells, and ſhame of ſhames,</l>
            <l>Where men ſhall iuſtly dare to fight and dye:</l>
            <l>And writers will not regeſter their names.</l>
            <l>When noming makes them liue Immortally.</l>
            <l>To ſhew how valiant men doe ſpend their blood,</l>
            <l>It doth each worthy heart with courage ſtrike,</l>
            <l>To Imitate the actions that are good,</l>
            <l>And by example to attemp the like.</l>
            <l>But when a man ſhall for a certaine know,</l>
            <l>That with his life, his memory muſt fall:</l>
            <l>And no Records his worthineſſe ſhall ſhow,</l>
            <l>Theſe meanes will make ſtarke Cowards of vs all.</l>
            <l>Then theſe poore lines ſhall make theſe men ſuruiue,</l>
            <l>Vnto the vtmoſt end of time or fate:</l>
            <l>They liu'd and dyed, and dead, are ſtill aliue,</l>
            <l>In Name, in Pame, in Earthly, Heauenly ſtate.</l>
            <l>And as for him that writ the Booke before,</l>
            <l>Let him write better, or elſe write no more.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:4"/>
            <head>The <hi>Dolphins</hi> danger and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: Being a Shippe of London of 220. Tunne, hauing in her but 36. men, and two Boyes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Almighty Creator, (who onely worketh wonders) confounding ſtrong things by weake meanes, as <hi>Dauids</hi> Sling, <hi>Samgars</hi> Goad, <hi>Sampſons</hi> Iaw-bone, <hi>Gedeons</hi> Pitchers, the great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Siſera</hi> and <hi>Holofernes</hi> kil'd by two ſeely weake Woemen. All theſe and innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble examples more there are both in diuine and humane Hiſtories, which demonſtrates that victory doth not conſiſt in the Arme of fleſh, but in the omnipotent Lord of Hoſts, and God of Battles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24000:5"/>The Conſideration of which makes vs with thankefulneſſe to commemorate this our great Deliuerance, from ſo imminent dangers, and ſharpe Aſſaults, as few, or none hath more cauſe to be thankfull for the like, and not to attribute any thing to my ſelfe being the Maiſter of the Ship, or with oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to puffe vp any of my Company, but giuing the glory to whom glory belongs, I proceed.</p>
            <p>About the end of this laſt yeare, our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires beeing accompliſht at Zant, our Ship called the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of London, of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of 220. Tunne, hauing in her 19. caſt Pieces, and 5. Murtherers 36. Men and two Boyes, the Maiſters name <hi>Edward Nichols,</hi> a man whoſe courage, induſtry, knowledge, and integrity, are manifeſted by his actions in former times, but now more particularly in this laſt and perilous aduenture, we being laden weyed our Anchor, and ſet ſaile from Zant the firſt of Ianuary 1616. with a faire gale of winde at North and by Eaſt the
8. of Ianuary, we had ſight of the Iland of Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine,<pb facs="tcp:24000:5"/>then the wind beeing come Weſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wee on the ninth day ſtood for
<hi>Callery,</hi> we came cloſe by two litle watch Towers, who ſhot two ſhot neere vs to giue warning to vs, that they would ſpeak with vs, which night would not permit, for if wee could haue ſent a ſhore to them, their intent was to haue informed vs of the Turkes men of war, which after we met withall to our coſt and perrill and theirs to, for theſe townes were not aboue two Leagues off from the place where wee made our fight. At night (being calme) we ſailed towards Cape Pola, which ſmall gale brought vs neere to the Cape the 11. day About 2. of the Clock af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone. Three Leagues Eaſtward of the aforeſaid Cape, we deſcryed a Satty, which is a ſmall coaſting Veſſell, ſent at that time for a ſcout or ſpye, belonging to the Turks men of Warr: who kept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of vs in the euening neere the Ile of Serdine, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the King of Spaine: The ſaid Satty putting forth a light aloft, to giue a ſigne to the reſt of his aſſociates that hee had eſpied<pb facs="tcp:24000:6"/>vs, and the more to delude vs, they let th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> light ſodainly fall, that we might immagine it to be the ſhooting of a Starre.</p>
            <p>The 12. of Ianuary in the morning about 4. of the clocke we had better ſight of the Sattie, and we perceiued that ſhe ſtood in to get betwixt the ſhore and vs, which made vs doubt ſhe had more fellowes not far off, as not long after wee found: the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. preſently ſent one to the top maſt head who preſently diſcouered 5. Ships more making towards vs before the wind being then at weſt South weſt, which the Maiſter with a proſpectiue glaſſe perceiu'd to be the Turks men of war. The firſt of them booming by himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wind with al his ſailes abroad, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out colours or Flag, yet at preſent boording he put his flag out as we immagined: After him came 2. ſhips more of greater burthen then the firſt, and next one more which put his Flag in the main top as we perceiued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward: then came the 5. and laſt much greater in bignes and force then any of the reſt, all ſtrongly prepared to offend and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend<pb facs="tcp:24000:6"/>in any Godles deſperate aſſault; our M. perceiuing their readines, made ſpeedy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for the incounter with our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and ſmall ſhot, and other defenſiue munition, firſt perſwading his men with moſt Chriſtian and manly Reſolution by prayer firſt to recommend their ſoules, their bodies, and their actions to their God and Sauiour, which being done they went to dinner, after which the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. againe exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them in this manner. Contrymen and fellowes, you ſee into what an exigent it hath pleaſed God to ſuffer vs to fall into, let vs remember that we are but men, and muſt die of neceſſity, when, where and how, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Gods knowledge &amp; appointment, but if it be his pleaſure, that this muſt be the laſt of our dayes, his will be done, and let vs for his glory, our ſoules welfare, our Countries honor &amp; the credit of our ſelues, fight it va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly to the laſt gaſpe: let vs prefer a noble death before a ſlauiſh life, &amp; if we die let vs die to gaine a better life, for mine own part qd. he, I will ſee that if we eſcape this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that if any be hurt &amp; maimd in the fight<pb facs="tcp:24000:7"/>they ſhall bee carefully prouided for their health and maintenance whilſt they liue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, therefore bee reſolute ſtand to it, heere is no ſhrinking, but force perforce we muſt be men or ſlaues, die with me, or if you will not, I by Gods grace will dye with you.</p>
            <p>Theſe cheerfull words had been ſufficient to put courage into faint hartles Cowards: but much more it emboldened vs that were feareles before, for wee all expected greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make proofe of the ſucceſſe: at which the Maiſter cauſed his Trumpets twice to haile them, but they not regarding vs, ſcornd to anſwer vs, then the M. went vp the poop and waued his ſword 3. or 4. times ouer his head, brandiſhing it with ſuch dreadles reſolution, as if the day had beene ours already: then the Trumpets ſounded a charge, which warlik noyſe inſpird vs with new courage, &amp; beeing within ſhot of them our M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. commanded his Gunner to make his leuell &amp; to ſhoot, went cloſe by his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that was neereſt vs, ſhot on purpoſe to miſſe him, as a warning what kind welcome<pb facs="tcp:24000:7"/>they were to haue at our hands at which the formoſt ſhip came vp to vs apace, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt becalmed, or with very little winde, returning vs worſe then wee ſent for their firſt ſhot kild vs a man, ſo betwixt vs for a good ſpace was a moſt furious encounter, they hauing aduantage of vs by reaſon of the winde, preſently layde vs a boord with one of their ſhippes, this was neere about eleauen of the clocke, then they ſounded their Trumpets, and gaue ſueh a ſhowt as if they had won the victory already. But God, that neuer leaues thoſe that put their confidence in him, cheared our Maiſter and Company with ſuch manly fortitude, that preſently our Trumpets ſounded and anſwered them with a charge. (Which Trumpeter was preſently ſlaine, as ſhalbe after related,) and the Boatſwaine winding his whiſtle, that pell-mell we fell to it, in ſuch feirce manner that their great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance had torne our ſhippe that wee vſed our Gunes cleare of the ports, for they had left vs no port on the quarters but all open,<pb facs="tcp:24000:8"/>but we not failing to pay them as well on their bow, to their great diſmaying, for we had not left them one man aliue from their maine-maſt forward; beſides we diſmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their ordinance, &amp; tore them ſo neer the water that their cheife Commanders were forced with their Cuttleaxes to beate their owne men, to force them to make more haſt to vngrapple from vs then they did to boord vs.</p>
            <p>All this time the Maiſter, Vigillently went to and frow encouraging his men, ſometimes in the Gunner roome, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at the healme, ſometimes on the port as ocaſion ſerued, and where his preſence was moſt needfull. This firſt fight conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued two howers, the ſhip was in burden, two hundred tunnes, or there abouts, and had in her 25. peices of ordinance, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 250. men, the Captaine of her, wee imagine was one
<hi>Walſingham,</hi> which ſhould be an Engliſh man by that name, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of himſelfe for ſo it ſignifide by his Flag in his maine top, they boorded vs on<pb facs="tcp:24000:8"/>our Larboord quarter, armd with fauchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hatchets, and halfe pikes, they ſtaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord vs halfe an hower, tearing vp our naileboords, vpon the poope and the Trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatch, but wee hauing a murtherer in the round houſe kept the larbboord-ſide cleare, whileſt our men with the other ordinance, and muskets, and a murtherer in our Trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatch, playd vpon them and their ſhip, yet for all this they paide our gallery with ſmal ſhot that we were much endangered, but at laſt we ſhot her through and through, and they vs likewiſe, that being fearefull to be ſunke ſhe bore a head from vs and lay by the lee to mend her leakes, this fight was ſo neere the ſhore, that the inhabitants ſet vp a glaſſe and found it laſted two howers and a halfe, and this was the firſt encounter in which was kild fiue men and a little boy, the manner how they were ſlaine ſhalbe at the end of the booke.</p>
            <p>Now the Second incounter as wee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was with Captaine
<hi>Kelleies</hi> Ship that<pb facs="tcp:24000:9"/>came likewiſe vp with his flag in the maine top, and another Ship with his Flag in the fore top, which Shippes were at leaſt three hundred tunne apeece or there abouts, and had in each of them twenty eight or thirty peeces of Ordinance, and about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred &amp; fifty men, ſo they laid vs aboard on the Starbord quarter, and the other on the Larbor, where entring our ſhip thicke and threefold, with their ſemiters, hatchets, halfe pikes and other weapons, put vs in great danger both of the loſſe of our Ship and our liues, for they performed much man-hood and many dangerous hazards, amongſt which there was one of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that deſperately went vp into our maine top to fetch downe our Flag, which being ſpied by the Steward of our Ship, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhot him with his Muſquet that hee fell tumbling vpon our decke, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Caſt ouerbord by their owne men, as they did the reſt, leauing the Flag hehind him, ſo theſe two ſhippes fought with vs with great reſolution, playing vppon vs
<pb facs="tcp:24000:9"/>with their Ordinance and ſmall ſhot, for the ſpace of an hower and a halfe, of whom we receiued ſome hurt, and likewiſe they of vs, but when they could not preuaile, nor any way make vs to yeeld, they bore vp and paſſed from vs to lay their ſhips by the leeto ſtop their leaks, for wee had grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly batterred them with our great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and this was the ſecond attempt they made vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Now for the third, there came one more of theirs ſhips of two hundred tunne that had 30. pieces of Ordinance, and at the leaſt two hundred and 50. men all well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided as might be, which was as we thought too great a number for vs, beeing ſo few in our ſhip, but God that was our friend gaue vs ſuch ſtrength and ſucceſſe that they lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle preuailed againſt vs, for at their firſt comming vp, notwithſtanding all their multitude of men, wee ſhot her quite thorough and thorough, we entertaind her with two minion and three ſacre, on our ſtarboard ſide, then ſhe fell to our Larboard<pb facs="tcp:24000:10"/>ſide, and then we welcom'd her with a ſacre in our bow, two minion and, one demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culuerin, which made her forſake vs and lye by the lee, as the others did before: but the other ſhip remaining, greater then the reſt, in burden 500. tunnes with 650. men, laid vs aboard on the Starbord ſide, and in that quarter they entred our ſhip, with their Semiters, Fauchions, halfe Pikes, and other weapons, running to and fro vpon the deck crying ſtill in the Turkiſh tongue, and ſome Engliſh, yeeld your ſelues, promiſing we ſhould be well vſed, and one third part of our goods deliuered backe, with ſuch like faire promiſes; at which one of our compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny told, the Maiſter of the large offer of the Turkes, perſwading him to yeeld, but the Maiſter replied, away villaine, I will neuer giue them part or quarter, whilſt I haue quarters to my body. Who beeing thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, ſome of our men plyed our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance againſt them, ſome played with the ſmall ſhot, ſome with other weapons, as ſwords and halfe Pikes and ſuch like, in<pb facs="tcp:24000:10"/>middeſt of which skirmiſh, it ſo happened by ill chance that they ſeeing that we would not yeeld to compoſition firde our ſhip in three places in the Maiſters Cabbin, the gallery, with wild fire balls caſt into the hold and ſo left vs, beſides our gunnes and theirs fired the Carpenters cabbin, that wee and the ſhip was fired, and in great danger to be loſt and caſt away, had not the Lord in his mercy preſerued vs, and ſent vs meanes happily to quench it, but now marke the accident, the fier being perceiued by our enemies to burne outragiouſly, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that our Shippe would haue therewith beene ſodainly burned to the water, they left vs to our fortunes, falling a ſterne from vs, and ſo wee put to the ſhoare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Towre, for ſome ſuccour, where wee let an Anchor fall thinking to ride there all that night, which wee had no ſooner done, but we ſaw the great ſhip that parted from vs, in our iudgement beare vpon vs, and at that time the ſhip that neuer boorded vs ſhot a peece of ordinance, while wee were<pb facs="tcp:24000:11"/>preparing for another incounter and ſo we were forced to wey our Anchor, and ſet ſayle to get better ſuccour, and the enemy being weary of our company hoyſt out their boates to mend their leakes, wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we put into the roade betweene the two little towers, where wee ſent our maymed gunner a ſhore to one of thoſe towers, to make ſhot at the enemy if need were, where we lay fiue daies, mending the bruiſes and leakes of our ſhip: the loſſes we receiued in the aforeſaide fight, were ſixe Men and one Boy, which were killed outright, and there were hurt eyght men and one Boy more: but the Lord doth know what damage we put them to, and what number wee ſlew in their ſhips.</p>
            <p>There is one thing more worthy of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berance of our Chirurgion whoſe name was <hi>Robert Groue,</hi> who as hee was dreſſing one of our men in the hold of our Ship, a Ball of Wildfire fell into his Baſon which he thinking to caſt ouer boord it fell vpon the decke, which had greatly indangered<pb facs="tcp:24000:11"/>vs but that hee reſolutly fell vpon it and rouling in it ſmothered it out with his body. The Turkes trumpeters were aboard and ſounded their Trumpets, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, our men aſſaulted them ſo fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they forced them off, and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaine (ſeeing them flye) moſt vndanted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a whiſtle blourd them to the skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, if ſo they durſt. The Captaines of three of their Ships were Engliſhmen, as we thinke, who tooke part with the Turks thus to rob and ſpoyle vpon the Ocean, their names were <hi>Walſingham, Kelley,</hi> and
<hi>Sampſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon the 13. of Ianuary there came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board certaine Spaniards in the morning betimes to witnes what hurts wee had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, who ſeing our men dead, went a ſhore with vs, and ſhowed vs where wee might bury them, but as wee wore buſie in making their graues, and couering the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with earth, there came ſayling by a Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Ship of twelueſcore tunne, which the enemy in the darke thought had beene vs,<pb facs="tcp:24000:12"/>and ſo let her paſſe, which had in her fiue or ſixe thouſand pounds, which had beene chaſed with thoſe men of warre that had fought with vs before, all which mony they brought in a long boate to this ſhore, and left in the ſhip onely three men, which were two Saylers and one Soldier, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards within two daies brought the ſaid ſhip into the Road of Callery, not any thing at all indangered, God be praiſed.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 15. of the ſame Month when we came from the burying of our men, &amp; had reſted our ſelues in our Shippe ſome two or 3. houres, as God would haue it, the wind began to blow a ſtrong gale, and by little &amp; little grew to be a terrible tempeſt, through which from Sunday night till Friday in the euening. wee lay in ſuch extremity of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as raine, winde, lightening and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that we thought we ſhould neuer haue got cleere from the Road where we lay: du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which ſtorme and tempeſt there dyed one of our men, that had beene hurt in the fight, whoſe body wecaſt ouerbord, into the<pb facs="tcp:24000:12"/>Sea, without any other buriall, and ſo when the winde and ſea a little calmed, wee ſet vp ſaile and came forward: but within three dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we buried 3. men more in the ſea, and the ſame afternoone we arriued in the Road of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and lay at anchor, where againe ſearching our Ship, we found it rent and torne in many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral places, ſo in Callery we mended our Ship, and hired certaine men there to help vs to ſtop her leakes, and fiſh her Maſts, and hauing all thinges fitting for our Voyage homewards, vpon the 30. day of Ianuary we committed our ſelues againe vnto the Sea, ſo leauing Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery wee came foreward with a Frenchman, who was bound to a place Oreſtone, ſome thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Leagues from Callery, where after two daies we left his company being the firſt day of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary, and after that putting forewards ſtill towards England, we are now by Gods aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſafely ariued at <hi>London,</hi> to the contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Owners, and the comfort of our ſelues that (by the Almighties protection) haue eſcaped ſo many dangers. <hi>God be praiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_casualties">
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>WAlter Penroſe,</hi> the firſt man kild, being ſhot in the belly.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Thomas Sheapheard</hi> quarter maiſter, his head ſhot off.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>William Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>te,</hi> Trumpetter, as he ſounded in the fight had one arme ſhot off, yet he ſounded till another great ſhot ſtroke off his other arme, with his Trumpet and all, then after hee was kild with a ſhot thorow the body.</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>William Raſſell,</hi> quarter maiſter, had me arme firſt ſhot off, afterward he was ſhot through and kild.</item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Iohn Sands,</hi> the crowne of his head ſhot off.</item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Beniamin Cornellius,</hi> a boy, ſhot in the throat, kild.</item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Dauid Fauſe,</hi> maiſters mate, ſhot in the groyne, kild.</item>
               </list> 
               <hi>Theſe men were kild outright and buries a ſhore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe 4 men dyed within 4 or 5 dayes, after were cast into the ſea.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>8 <hi>Io: Blackatar,</hi> quarter Mr. his leg maym'd &amp; burnt blind, yet he labored to quench the ſhip beeing fired.</item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Thomas Worger,</hi> a youth, the Maſters ſeruant, his ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der blade ſhot off and liued three dayes.</item>
                  <item>10 <hi>William Iames,</hi> Trumpetter, burnd with wilde fire, that he flamed like a fiery man all ouer, then <hi>Iohn Roff</hi> Purſer caſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on him, to quench him, he liued 5 dayes in great paine: in the fight an arrow came betwixt the Maiſters legs at the helme and ran into the ſaid <hi>Iames</hi> his leg which the Maiſterpuld out.</item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Iohn Preſtin,</hi> a youth, kild with a musket.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe following, were maymd and hurt, and are liuing.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert May</hi> Maiſters mate, ſhot in the thigh,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho Wright,</hi> gunner, with ſhot &amp; ſplintars hurt in 12. places.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Dauiell,</hi> burnt with powder, and loſt an eye.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roger Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>er,</hi> wounded in the head with ſplinters.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Downes,</hi> the Maiſters boy, ſhot in the belly, liues.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe men are aliue vnhurt.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Nichols</hi> Maſter, ſhot with a ſmall ſhot, that tore his hoſe and ſtockings through, and gaue his legge a ſcarre, and 4 times ſhot through the hoſe. <hi>Fra. Conſtable</hi> Boat ſwaine, <hi>Iohn Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he</hi> Purſer. <hi>William Lucas</hi> Carpenter. <hi>The. Hob</hi> Gunners mate,
<hi>Wil. Moore quarter</hi> Gunner. <hi>Wil. Coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Steward <hi>Rob. Grone</hi> Chirurgion. <hi>Iohn Adiney</hi> Couper. <hi>Chriſto. Auſten</hi> Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Lee,</hi> Boatſons mate. <hi>Wil. Renfree quar:</hi> M. <hi>Will. Chalicom, Iſake Watlington,</hi> Trumperters.
<hi>Thee: Anderſon, Tho. Spurden Nicho. Wilkinſon, Henry Low, Cornelius Scot, Philip</hi> a welchman, Saylers the reſt were paſſengers.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:24000:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
